[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at
SE-R SC radio is brought to you by the
it computer society and by It software
Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software for software engineering radio
this is Robert blumen today I have With
Me Andy sudman Andy is the CTO of
Fairwinds a kubernetes service provider
he's previously held roles as Sr
principal engineer and director of R&D
and Technology he works with
infrastructure spanning major Cloud
providers and verticals he is a graduate
of the Colorado School of Minds Andy
welcome to software engineering radio
thanks for having me and today Andy and
I will be talking about setting up and
managing kubernetes cluster we've done a
few episodes on kubernetes already 446
334 and 319 and it was mentioned in 440
on get Ops we also have some recorded
content on kubernetes coming up that we
don't have an episode number yet so
we've covered it quite a bit I'd like to
just do one background question if you
could give a really brief synopsis of
what is kubernetes and what problem does
it solve and then we'll be talking more
about how to set it up yeah sure I happy
too so kubernetes at its core is a
container orchestrator right we use it
to run containers across multiple
machines and do lots of things with
containers so at its heart it's an API
that allows us to describe the desired
state of containers running across
multiple machines so that's probably the
simplest way to define kubernetes and
how we we think about it so I want to
start out with let's say an organization
has decided they want to migrate to
kubernetes or adopt kubernetes as their
orchestration platform how did that
conversation go to get to the point and
what Alternatives did they consider and
rule out I think that's a really
interesting way to ask that question
because most of the time I get asked
what should we think about when we're
moving to kubernetes people have already
made the decision I think it's important
to think about the reasons why so lots
of different alternatives to consider I
think one of the biggest things to think
about with mov toes is taking on
complexity you're adding so many layers
of complexity to your stack do you
really need that level of customization
do you need that level of control are
you building a platform on top of that
are you serving multiple teams and
multiple apps if you just have one app
and it's already containerized and you
don't need to run it across you don't
need a ton of control over how it's run
and you only have one maybe don't use
kubernetes and use something like Cloud
run or fargate on eks or one of the
other many other ways to run containers
so I think thinking about the balance of
complexity versus features that you get
from running kubernetes is super
important I'm going to ask you a
question question where the answer is
going to be it depends but do the best
you can it's a mediumsized organization
that has some different products and
they want to get all in on kubernetes
how many clusters are they going to end
up with and what are driving factors in
triggering when you can run certain
things on the same cluster when you need
a new cluster and how much overhead is
there for each cluster yeah this is a
question we get a lot and the answer is
almost always two you need one non-
production cluster and one production
cluster and beyond that kubernetes has
so much built-in ability to segment
workloads in different ways and control
who has access to what that it's very
uncommon to really need especially in a
medium to small sized organization to
need more than just the nonpr and the
prod cluster you have to have that
separation between non-production and
production because you need to be able
to test changes that are cluster wide
and you can't safely do that in
production I have seen companies run
massive single clusters for the entire
organization prod and nonpr and that
usually turns into a bit of a disaster
so things to think about when you're
segmenting workloads are they
particularly noisy in one particular
area of resource utilization there's
different ways to segment that out but
sometimes a separate node group is
necessary you should always utilize
namespaces as much as possible because
they give you a very cheap segmentation
line to draw between different areas in
your clusters I think I hit all the
points of the question yeah now my
understanding it maybe I'm wrong about
this but kubernetes is single Regent
generally that is the case most
implementations of kubernetes allow you
to run multiple availability zones in
the same region but running cross
regions generally not recommended mostly
because of network Transit issues and
not being able to sort of make the
cluster be completely aware of what
network topology looks like between
different segments of the cluster if I
have a product and I want to run it on
Multi regions that would imply I'm going
to need one cluster per region is that
correct that's typically how we
recommend folks do it yeah I've seen
Solutions where especially in in Google
where networking is a little bit flatter
where you can run multi- region clusters
but typically we run one per region a
small company that starts because they
have one product idea so you put that
out on your kubernetes cluster
mediumsized company that has multiple
products are you going to run veral
products all on your same prod cluster
or are there going to be different kinds
of considerations of could be anything
and maybe you could include it in your
answer of why you need to put each
product on its own cluster or maybe not
maybe not all end to one yeah yeah so
typically like I said earlier we
recommend all prod workloads in a single
prod cluster this is just from a
complexity and overhead standpoint right
each additional cluster you have to keep
things up to date you have to update the
cluster itself now most of the reasons
that I see for segmenting products
between clusters or at the business
level I need to maybe keep all of my
workloads for one product in a specific
AWS account so that I can do much easier
billing segmentation and understand
which product costs more and so usually
I I think about cost allocation and
things like that when I when I think
about running multiple clusters just to
simplify that now there's plenty of
tools to do that stuff in a single
cluster which it's much more complex to
split a shared cluster
up from a cost perspective and from a
effort perspective you have multiple
Services you're going to be running on
this cluster that could include things
like
cicd that is deploying things onto the
cluster and you've got your dashboards
and monitoring that monitor the cluster
do you put it all on your Dev cluster
say we're going to use CI on dev to
deploy on dev and monitor it from Dev or
is there ever a reason why you want to
put monitoring and alerting or other
functions on their own cluster so you
can have resiliency or manage things
separately yeah that's an interesting
question I think the the first thing
that I I pick out with that question is
the assumption that you're running your
cicd and your monitoring in cluster I
think typically for a small to
mediumsized organization it makes much
more sense to pay a an outside vendor to
do those things for you so we're heavy
users of data dog we're heavy users of
Circle C there's lots of cicd systems
out there and so if it's not your core
competency and you don't want to have a
team that has to manage those things
don't run them yourself and don't run
them in kubernetes now if you are going
to run them there are arguments to be
made for running a third sort of
management cluster or tooling cluster
that will allow you to run those those
bits in a in a separate fashion and then
just have all the other clusters report
up to them and things like that cicd
workloads can be especially Troublesome
in kubernetes because they're they're
shortlived job style workloads that can
consume a ton of resources really fast
and then go away so at the very least a
separate node group for those sorts of
things and then the question of prod
versus non-prod with your cicd system is
an interesting one typically it's
probably easiest to to have one per
environment but then you've got the
management overhead of running your cicd
system twice so what does that look like
maybe a separate cluster is Justified in
this case and as you said earlier the
answers always includes a depends right
absolutely that's the catchall answer
for everything now I want to move on
talking about we've made some of these
strategic decisions and we're now
looking at setting up a cluster at least
two of the options I'm aware of are you
build it yourself or you use a manage
cluster offering from one of the cloud
service providers Amazon and Google I'm
aware have manage kubernetes offering is
there ever any reason to build your own
now or would you always let somebody
else build it for you the answer is
almost always let somebody else build it
for you we've run clusters since before
eks existed and we ran cops clusters and
that works and it's fine but it's just
so much more management overhead the
only time that I say you you know build
your own cluster is when you have a
really specialized use case that
requires you to run a very specific
configuration of your control plane and
honestly those configurations are very
rare I can't actually think of good
examples anymore there used to be
several good examples but they've all
been incorporated into the kuber's entry
control plane and they options that you
can just use you don't have to enable
them specifically so it's very rare that
I recommend running anything other than
your your cloud provider managed control
plane we recently did episode 571 on
multicloud governance the topic was disc
discuss there is how the definition of
what is the cloud is becoming less clear
there's the old joke about the t-shirt
that says the cloud is someone else's
computer but there are emerging
Technologies where you can incorporate
Hardware you own into one of the cloud
service providers managed scope if you
are in a situation where you own a bunch
of your own on Prem computers are you
now obliged to build your own cluster
there or can you get a vendor to manage
a cluster for you and you bring your own
Hardware that's a great question and
know I'll be honest I haven't done any
on Prem Hardware in five and a half
years since my last role at working at
ready talk but I have heard good things
or interesting things at least about
some of the managed offerings that allow
you to incorporate your own Hardware
into a kubernetes cluster and from my
perspective as a as a cloud expert that
feels like the best way to work on a on
Prem to Cloud migration if that's the
long-term goal of that situation but if
you are running your own internal
Hardware I know there are other options
as well from companies like VMware to
run kubernetes on that Hardware as well
so in general managed is probably the
best way to go building your own control
plan from scratch is a lot of overhead
frankly I was surprised when I got
exposed to kubernetes the how much is
not in the base layer how components you
have to add to get to the point where
you have a functioning cluster which is
what you want you may not really care
that much which to give one example
which DNS provider is used as long as it
works how opinionated are the cloud
service providers managed offerings how
many decisions do they make for you to
get to that point where you have a
integrated workable system yeah so you
mentioned the DNS provider that one's a
little bit interesting because it's core
to kubernetes right it's the the heart
of service discovering kubernetes you
can't really run kubernetes without a
DNS provider so in that particular
instance the cloud providers are very
very opinionated but as soon as you get
beyond that point they become less
opinionated they give you an API and you
can run whatever you want on top of that
a including different cnis container
network interfaces different storage
drivers different options for just about
everything so in all of the like
standard kubernetes offerings I'd say
they're very not opinionated in any way
you start getting into things like gke
autopilot then you're allowing the cloud
provider to make decisions for you and
get opinionated which for some companies
is the right choice in order to reduce
that level of complexity but in general
it's just an API a kubernetes API and
then beyond that you install the rest of
your we call them add-ons you said a
couple things I want to follow up on the
gke autopilot say more about what that
is so GK autopilot is a sort of a more
lock down version of gke there's a lot
of policy and rules associated with how
you can deploy to it there's limitations
on what you're allowed to deploy for
example you can't deploy anything to a
gke autopilot cluster without a CPU and
memory request and then there are
certain rules about how big they have to
be how small they can be for a long time
they didn't allow really the creation of
any crds custom resource definitions I
think that has since changed but it's a
sort of a guardrails included version of
gke you mentioned the cni first what
does that stand for and what is it yeah
the container networking interface is
the the softwar defined Network layer
that all of your pods and thus your
containers will run inside of now what
that looks like is very different from
cni to cni we'll take eks for example
because it's the one that we use most
often by default you get the AWS VPC cni
which uses an AWS network interface on
each instance for the pods and so you
get actual in VPC routable IP addresses
for each pod if you choose to do it that
way there's a lot of other examples out
there the original one that most folks
are probably familiar with is flannel
and then there's Calico on top of that
and then there's psyllium there's a
whole bunch of options out there if you
are running on a cloud service provider
is there ever a situation where you're
going to want to use a different cni the
one that is built into the service
providers managed offering or did they
pretty much get it right for their
situation and you should move on and
operate your business that's a really
tough question answer I think in most
cases that's true there are limitations
to all of them the popular one that
folks will like to site on the AWS VPC
one is that it eats a lot of IP
addresses because you're giving an IP
address to each pod there's a lot of Ip
overhead and so in an ipv4 space you can
run out of IP addresses in a smaller
size VPC pretty quickly so that's one
downside to consider if you're running
like thousands and thousands of small
workloads maybe coming up with an
alternative strategy for managing those
IP addresses is important I'd say for
the you know 85 90% use case whatever
the cloud provider gives you is going to
be the most straightforward and they're
going to have the most expertise in it
and give you the most support on it if
you go and install psyllium on top of
awek then you're going to get a lot of
times you go to AWS support and they'll
be like well you're running cium go talk
to the cium folks we can't help you I'm
going to guess you'll say yes to this
should you use the service providers
container registry as the cluster
container registry I don't know that's
necessarily A Hard yes I think it can
make things easier for you for sure if
you have multicloud strategy definitely
not go with something centralized that
you can manage from one place if you've
got you know if you're already paying
Docker Docker hub's not a terrible
option you get additional benefits from
using something like Quay where you get
container scanning although the cloud
providers starting to add that now too
that's very much a how do you want to
store your artifacts question and not a
kubernetes question in my opinion it's
more of a traditional software like
where are we going to keep our artifacts
do we have an artifactory instance
already well maybe we should use that as
our registry do we have something else
going on that that makes more sense it's
not a horribly complex question because
it's an oci registry like it's it's an
artifact store if you have artifactory
are you going to run that on kubernetes
or where would you run it if not good
question if you have artifactory you're
probably already running it somewhere
right maybe it doesn't make sense to
change that maybe it makes sense to move
it into kubernetes just from a
management perspective we're going to
manage all of our things on kubernetes
there's a whole slew of Articles out
there that are you know should I move
everything to kubernetes or should I not
you've got a whole stateful question
there with artifactory like is it
running its art is it keeping its
artifacts on dis and maybe we we don't
necessarily want to run that in
kubernetes I haven't run artifactory in
a long time so I'm not an expert on that
specific use case but questions about
storage and things that are typical of
running any app in kubernetes would be
applicable Andy reading about this space
I see a lot of this day zero day one day
two what are those days and what happens
on each
one that's an interesting question our
uh marketing folks I think would tell me
to start moving away from that
terminology because it's a little bit
Antiquated perhaps but I I think the
heart of it is really thinking about
your level of maturity within kubernetes
right or within any system the finops
foundation likes to use the terminology
crawl walk run I think that's a great
way to describe the same thing day Zero
you don't have a cluster you don't know
anything about kubernetes you're not
maybe you don't even have containerized
applications although that's becoming
very rare these days and so so you just
need a cluster and you don't need all
this complexity you don't need addition
additional features or things like that
you just need to learn about how to get
an app into kubernetes get it running
and keep it running reliably when we
start talking about day one day two
which often get munged together pretty
quickly we start to think about more
advanced topics like how am I enforcing
policy in kubernetes how am I optimizing
resources in kubernetes how am I
deploying to kubernetes in a more
efficient manner or am I deploying
correctly and then we start thinking
about more about security and things
like that as well one of the things that
drives the adoption of kubernetes or any
kind of scheduled orchestration is it's
very good at scaling Individual Services
up or down so you can optimize your
resource spend but if your cluster also
could not scale up or down you might end
up with a lot of virtual machines that
you're leasing that aren't doing any
work do the managed service providers
offer integration with their own VM Auto
scaling so you can scale the cluster
itself up or down yes absolutely we
consider the ability to autoscale the
cluster a core ability of kubernetes and
we run it everywhere we run kubernetes
it varies from cloud provider to cloud
provider so eks at its heart the nodes
are run as autoscaling groups in eks so
if you're familiar with those you can
use the sort of standard ASG scaling
mechanisms those aren't necessarily
aware of kuber in any way so there's a
couple of other projects on top of that
that can work a little bit better
there's a kubernetes repo called
autoscaler includes the cluster
autoscaler that is a fairly
straightforward add-on that you can run
in your cluster it works with most if
not all of the major Cloud providers and
what it does is it watches for the need
for a new pod so when you spin up a new
pod the scheduler tries to say this pod
goes here in the cluster based on the
resources that it's requesting and if it
can't find a node to put that on then
the cluster autoscaler will generate a
new one and likewise over time it will
watch for empty ones and scale them out
and that's a fairly simple and
unsophisticated I quy fingers around
unsophisticated it's relatively complex
but it's not super aware of the topology
of the cluster when it does this it's
just do I need a node or do I not
there's other projects out there like
Carpenter which is a newer one for AWS
clusters currently that will it's of
replicates the Schuler and runs multiple
scenarios to see what type of node it
should be adding and or can it compact
the cluster into a smaller group of
nodes and so that's a popular one in AWS
right now and then in gke you get Auto
scaling for your node groups out of the
box it's just included you can turn it
on from the console if you want you can
say minimum nodes maximum nodes and it
works using that that similar cluster
autoscaler logic that I talked about
first and then the other Cloud providers
I'm not intimately aware of their
built-in abilities but the cluster
autoscaler works with all of them and
we've been using cluster autoscaler for
five or six years now since the early
days of kubernetes in your kubernetes
requests you can tell the a particular
service that needs a certain amount of
memory or number of cores but it can
also have specialized requests like
needs to run on a node that has ssds or
gpus are these cluster Auto scalers are
they schedu or aware where you'll
probably get the right kind nodes you
need for where the workload it needs to
launch so that's true of the the more
modern ones like carpenter carpenter is
very good at this it's one of its main
advertised features is it sees all of
those various requests about node types
and gpus and things like that and it
will attempt to pick a node for that
workload the traditional cluster Autos
scaler is not really aware of those and
so you have to be careful about making
sure that you've organized your node
groups in such a way that that if I need
gpus I have a node group that has gpus
available and I use a node selector that
forces it to be scheduled on that type
of node and then the cluster autoscaler
can scale that group to accommodate more
pods but you have to make sure those
nodes are sort of available already or
that node group type is available
already whereas Carpenter will just pick
a new node out of its P out of its list
of nodes which by default is every node
type in AWS which you might want to tune
a little bit but it will do just about
anything you ask it to so it's a little
bit more uh intelligent that way sounds
like the problem of autoscaling the
cluster then you would really need to
autoscale each node group somewhat
independently of each other node group
although there may be some services that
could run on more than one node group
but it sounds like it's a complicated
problem it definitely is and that's why
Carpenter was created was to sort of
solve a lot of those issues with the
cluster the original cluster autoscaler
and make that process easier
so
definitely engineering workflows can be
a mess from prioritizing Sprint tasks to
explaining technical diagrams you're
spending more time explaining work and
less time doing it mirro brings all your
work together seamlessly in one online
visual workspace create diagrams inl or
mermaid run sprints and create jira or
as your tasks and Miro instantly go from
idea to action without switching to
different tools get your first three
boards free when you sign up today at
mirro.com slmp podcast that's M
o.com
podcast now let's say we we're going
ahead we're going to have the two
clusters ER command maybe we're multi-
regions so maybe we end up with five
clusters because prod is in three
regions
what kind of tooling are you going to
use to spin up the Clusters do you
recommend infrastructure as code
approach absolutely huge advocate of
infrastructures code we use terraform we
use palumi in some places I know there's
a bit of drama with a capital D in the
terraform Community right now but
infrastructure is code pretty much an
absolute in our world we typically use
the cloud provider agnostic tools such
as terraform because we operate across
multiple clouds but I do know some folks
that are strictly running an AWS that
love cloud formation never been a a
personally huge fan but I'm also always
multic Cloud so I don't really get a
choice I want to talk a little bit more
about stateful applications but let's
assume for the moment you have a
stateful application and all your state
is in something that's durable like a
database or a storage Mount do you look
at the terraform cluster as an ephemeral
resource where you could lose it and
then you could rebuild it but with your
terraform from scratch if need be or if
you decide to expand into a new region
you could essentially spin it all up
with a minimal amount of work yeah
that's pretty much exactly how we treat
our clusters we typically try to keep
State out of it as much as possible and
that's a a very valid Dr strategy a
disaster recovery strategy if you're not
planning to have a warm standby or
something like that if your cluster is
completely stateless and you can
recreate it from your infrastructures
code in minutes then having a hot
standby cluster or a failover cluster
may not be necessary depending on your
Disaster Recovery needs were you ever in
a situation where either you lost
cluster you had to rebuild it or you
were doing a Dr and you were doing
exactly what we just said we practice
that scenario every every year we're
moving towards quarterly but we do try
that scenario out on a regular basis
just to validate that we can do it so I
think I'm lucky enough knock on wood to
say that I haven't had to do it in a
live situation before a full Regional
outage is a very rare occurrence thank
goodness so I don't think I've done it
on the fly but we definitely practice it
did you uncover anything like oh there's
that one thing and someone changed it
but it didn't get automated or something
that needs to be changed it's outside of
our
automation that's exactly why we
practice it and why we want to do it
every quarter because every time we do
it we find some rough edges where the
deploy process changed or we missed this
spot that we need to change the region
or something along those lines so
practicing those Dr Drills is is super
important to make sure that you catch
those edge cases each time we do it the
list gets smaller and we get a little
quicker at it so definitely takes
practice though I don't know if you
would agree with this but I I read
someone's opinion is that kubernetes was
really developed to run State less
applications and the state flow was a
bit of a an add-on it is true it's C
does not have any native method for
offering state so you end up importing
something from your cloud service
provider can you talk about what some of
the approaches are for obtaining state
from the cloud service yeah definitely
and I would totally agree with that I
think kubernetes was designed in it
originally to to run a standard
stateless API kind of your simplest use
case is kind of what it was built around
and the stateful stuff's gotten a lot
better but I still generally recommend
folks use their cloud provider for
maintaining State and that depends on
what kind of state you need in our case
it's mostly databases and so in that
case you've got your RDS or your Google
cloudsql to run your database and then
there are best practices around all of
those services for running them highly
available with backups and snapshots and
all of those good things to make sure
that you don't lose data but then you
also have your object stores so we make
Havey use of S3 as well for doing object
storage and then beyond that you've got
NFS right you've got your EFS stores
that can be beneficial in some ways if
you need shared storage but also
performance can be lacking so there's a
ton of different options for storage
from every cloud provider and almost
always you can find one that'll do what
you need to do so you've got your
cluster up you've got some stuff
deployed on it and you want it to become
visible to the outside world so
customers can use it what are the
addition steps and addons to get to that
point and I I should also mention you're
probably running inside a private VPC so
you may need to do things both in
kubernetes and at your cloud service
provider level yeah so this is where
your add-ons come into play that's what
we we call them add-ons I don't know if
that's a common term honestly but I've
been talking about this topic for a long
time I think one of the earliest blog
articles I wrote about kubernetes was
what all the stuff you need to make it
run for you and so so there's this group
of applications that I I personally call
the trifecta because I love it so much
personally because I used to have to run
all these things manually in a Data
Center and these three things together
make all of that go away and so the
three things are external DNS which is a
automation tool for updating your Cloud
providers DNS records to point to your
applications in kubernetes based on the
kubernetes objects themselves there's CT
manager which uses the Acme protocol and
you can hook it up to Let's encrypt to
do automated certificate generation and
rotation so by default it'll generate a
90day certificate for your
applications and renew it every 60 and
then the third one is an Ingress
controller of some kind and so in
kubernetes there's the concept of an
Ingress which is a built-in API
object and that object itself doesn't do
anything unless you have a controller to
satisfy it essentially and so there's
lots of different Ingress controllers
out there most of them are based on
Technologies you might be familiar with
outside of kubernetes like engine X or
ha proxy or traffic we typically
recommend to start out the engine X
Ingress controller or the project called
Ingress engine X which is very confusing
naming but essentially what it does is
it creates a config for engine X inside
of a proxy an engine X procy that's
running in the cluster to Route traffic
to your pods based on that Ingress
definition that you create and that will
also trigger those other two projects to
do their work so essentially the end
result of these three projects together
is that when I create a service in
kubernetes I rattle about 20 lines of
yaml to Define an Ingress object that
says this is the host name that I want
this is the pod that's servicing that
service and what you'll get out of the
box is a route through a load balancer
to that a DNS name and a certificate to
go with it so it automates all of that
extra stuff around deploying a service
and making it publicly available that
you wouldn't have had out of the box I
want to drill down into some of the
components of that response let's start
with DNS the DNS you could either have
an a record or a c name which is an
alias to another DNS what does the DNS
point at because all of your kubernetes
is inside a VPC and it has its own
networking so is that where the load
balancer comes in yeah so it's you have
to sort of couple that question with the
Ingress controller or with a little bit
of knowledge of kubernetes services so a
kubernetes service is another API object
that you create and if you you create it
in a certain way if you give it a
certain type it will have a different
external endpoint or it won't have an
external endpoint at all so we'll take
the simplest external use case where you
say I want a service of type load
balancer well that will trigger Reet is
to create a load balancer in a public
subnet that's accessible and then
essentially attach that load balancer to
your pod and I don't know how complex we
want to get with the mechanism on how
that works but essentially what it does
is it creates a load balancer that
routes traffic to your pod and then
external DNS if you're in AWS will
create a cname to that load balancer
name in your DNS provider of choice now
often that'll be Route 53 if you're in
AWS but you could also use cloud flar
you could also use one of many other DNS
providers and who or what is creating
that DNS entry is that done as part of
the orchestration when you request the
load balancer service no so that's
actually the separate project external
DNS so that's actually a thing that you
would install in your cluster and it
runs as a service and it watches for
these objects to get created so it'll
watch for a service that has an
annotation that says hey I need a DNS
name and it'll say okay I see this
service it's got a load balancer
attached that information's as in the
status of the actual service in
kubernetes and so it sees that and along
with its configuration to say this is my
DNS provider it'll go to the DNS
provider and say okay I'm going to put
in this DNS name with this C name and
then it also uses a text record to keep
track of which records it has created so
there's a little bit of safety mechanism
built in there too got it so external
DNS is a kubernetes service and it uses
the kubernetes watch mechanism to be
aware of when it needs to either spin up
or tear down records in the cloud
provider DNS or whichever DNS you use
now that leads into a side question
which I was going to ask but your
kubernetes service is able to use
certain of the cloud service provider
apis we've talked about requesting a
load balancer service modifying DNS
cloud service providers have very fine
grained permission models of who exactly
can do what so is there a step when
you're bootstrapping the kubernetes
cluster where you have to decide what
permissions the cluster has and those
permissions then get delegated to
specific services that run within the
cluster yes there's definitely there's
multiple mechanisms by which you can do
IAM mappings or permissions mappings to
kubernetes Services the most common one
that's in used now well let's just say
back in the day originally we would give
permissions just to the nodes themselves
now this is a little bit of a security
problem because if the whole node has
the permissions to act on the cloud
provider than any pod running on that
node regardless of whether it needs it
or not has those permissions so in the
last three or four years we've moved to
what I refer to as workload identity
different Cloud providers have different
names for it so in gke it's actually I
just forgot the name for GK in AWS it's
irsa which is IM am roles for services
accounts and so what you do is you
create an IM role that has a certain set
of permissions and then you say this
service account in kubernetes is allowed
to assume that role and then you tell
the individual service hey this is the
role that you should use to do cloud
provider actions so the end result is
each pod that is running as part of say
the external DNS service can only assume
the role that we've given it for
external DNS which means now through
aws's am I can give it as many or as few
permissions as I want if I only want it
to be able to modify a single specific
DNS Zone I can restrict it to that and
so you have that fine level of control
that you have at the cloud provider
level all the way down to the individual
pod level in critics okay so we're going
to set up a role that's let's call it
DNS record read write and this DNS
external DNS service through these
bindings will be able to assume that
role and it's a able to create and
delete DNS records but it doesn't have
the ability to create a new database or
EBS or any other of the million things
you could do in AWS that you don't want
your DNS provider to do exactly great
now so we're going through these layers
the load balancer which is provided by
the cloud service provider then that is
going to proxy to the Ingress is that
the next step in the pipeline yeah so in
the event of when we're using an Ingress
controller let's just use engine X for
our example here because it's the
easiest one to talk about because a lot
of folks are familiar with engine X
outside of kubernetes there will be
several engine X pods running in the
cluster and they'll have their own
kubernetes service that is attached to
that load balancer and so all DNS
records that point to the Ingress that
go through the Ingress controller will
point to that single load balancer so
it's a nice way to consolidate all of
your load balancers into one and then
that will feed through engine X and so
engine X will have gotten a configur a
server block right that says this host
name goes to these pods basically and
then it will route the traffic it will
forward the traffic onto that pod as you
just pointed out you might be running
several instances of the engine X ingr
so the load balancer it needs to be up
to dat on how many instances there are
and what their addresses are does the
load balancer use the overlay Network or
external IPS or how what set of ips is
the load balancer proxying to to get to
the Ingress so in in your most standard
configuration in most cases what will
happen is the engine X will will be set
up as a load balancer service but
underneath that is what's called a node
Port service and so this exposes a
single high port on every single node in
the cluster that routesy traffic to that
engine X instance and so essentially the
AWS load balancer will be routing
traffic to every single node or it'll
have in its list every single node on
that specific port and that node list is
kept up to date by the by a kubernetes
control plane component that's managing
the load
balancer called the controller manager
so we're talking about all the steps
that the routing goes through to get
from the external world to your kuber's
cluster we have the cloud service
providers load balancer the node Port
service which is a type of load
balancing and then it goes to the
Ingress which is another load balancing
I count three load balancers that seems
a bit overdone to me is this a good
solution or did it have to be done that
way because of how the kubernetes
network works that's a great question I
I'll start with the first one is this a
good solution likely no you know at the
end of the day it's probably not a
terrible solution and it does work I'll
start by saying that a lot of other
Solutions are out there now that changed
this Behavior right that was the default
as of you know two three years ago it's
still the default depending on how you
configure and so a lot of things have
been mitigated for instance you can
instruct kubernetes to only let nodes
that are running the actual pods for the
workload to be included in the load
balancer so it'll actually fail the
health checks for the nodes that are not
running the actual pods receiving
traffic so that eliminates one potential
hop where you end up on a node that
doesn't have the actual pod running and
then it gets forwarded to the other node
so that's one hop potential hop removed
and I think that would have actually
been a fourth in your list there and
then we have things like the AWS VPC cni
which I talked about earlier which
allows in newer more advanced config
configurations for you to create a
Target group for a network load balancer
that includes just the pods so it routs
directly to the pods skipping the whole
node hop as well so I do think it was
sort of a maybe not a necessity but a
necessity for keeping things simple and
straightforward in the earlier days of
kubernetes and making things work for
everyone as much as possible and all the
cloud providers but there's a lot of
different configurations you can
introduce now depending on what cloud
provider you're in or what Ingress
controller you're actually using to
simplify these networking scenarios if
that's needed for you the last piece you
mentioned was certificate manager is
that another service that runs on
kubernetes that does similar to DNS it
watches for when there's a need for
certificate and then obtains it from
your ca yep that is exactly what it is
so it watches for different things in
the cluster it has its own custom resour
source definition so you can just
request aert as a yaml object so I can
say give me the certificate and
depending on how you have it configured
what CA it reaches out to and things
like that it'll generate aert the other
thing that it does is What's called the
Ingress shim which is it watches for
Ingress objects that have a specific
annotation and then a TLS configuration
within them and it will automatically
generate that certificate object and
then fulfill it like it would if you
created the certificate and that last
step then did I understand certificate
manager it would somehow deploy the
private key into your Ingress so Ingress
can terminate the TLs essentially yes
what it does is it creates the
certificate which then generates the
secret which contains the the key and
the CT and then enginex Ingress will
actually pick up that secret name as
this is the sert I'm supposed to use so
the TLs specification in the Ingress
says what secret name to use and then C
manager just fulfills that basically got
it so it's handing it off through the
secret rather than going directly from C
manager to Ingress correct and on the
topic of Ingress I'm aware there are
many popular load balancers enginex
which you mentioned certainly very
popular you have a bunch of others if
organization has pre-existing preference
for one of the reverse proxies they like
is there likely to be an Ingress that's
built around around that particular
reverse proxy it's quite possible I
don't know that I'm up to date on the
list of all the possible reverse proxies
out there but it's quite likely that
there there may be an Ingress controller
out there for it and you do also
mentioned Secrets which is an area I
wanted to get into the kubernetes
secrets are not very good you may decide
they're not secret enough for something
security that that you need to have what
do you think of the builtin and what are
some options for doing better yeah I was
going to say I wanted to start by
addressing that that statement that
kubernetes Secrets aren't very good I
think kubernetes Secrets get a bad W
because by default they're base 64 and
codin and a lot of folks like sort of
confuse that for encryption which
hopefully we all know is not encryption
they're not intended to be encrypted
however Secrets as an object in
kubernetes are treated with the respect
by the API that a secret should be
treated with they have fine grain
controls over permissions they are
stored in a separate area of the state
store ETD for your cluster and they're
not printed in any sort of built-in
logging or anything like that so they
are treated the way that Secrets should
be I think what folks take a little bit
of objection with is that they're not
encrypted within at CD so that's a
question of your risk tolerance and your
threat profile right how much you want
to protect the secrets eted itself is
probably running on an encrypted at rest
storage mechanism
and maybe encrypted in other ways and so
and all of your communication with that
CD will be encrypted by default and so
if you don't have the need to store them
encrypted within sedd so if you don't
think your eted database is going to get
leaked in plain text to the world then
it's probably Overkill to introduce one
of these other solutions that being said
there's lots of other Solutions out
there that can make Secrets different or
handle them differently so there's the
ability to encrypt them within at CD
using your cloud provider key storage so
KMS in actually all the clouds I think
they all call it KMS because it's Key
Management Service and so there's the
ability to run a controller that
essentially has AWS or gcp permissions
to use that key to encrypt the actual
secret before it goes into etcd and when
you retrieve it I question the value of
this because now you're just offloading
the encryption to a different place in
the cloud provider is it truly more
secure and I'd have to draw that threat
model out to really determine but it
always seemed a bit of Overkill if
you're really really concerned about
Secrets Management in kubernetes what I
recommend is just offloading your
secrets into a different place entirely
so using something like hashy Corps
Vault to store your secrets or your AWS
uh secret manager gcp secret manager and
then referencing that directly from
either your application or using a
controller in the cluster to give you
access to those secrets on an as needed
basis and with fine grain I am
permissions Okay so we've covered a
bunch of pieces in that stack for
getting traffic into the cluster going
to change directions now and talk about
some of the security features kubernetes
does offer ro-based access control is
that going to be a default setting or
should you turn that on and should
everyone be using that by default it is
turned on in pretty much every instance
of kuber that I'm aware of these days
it's been around for long enough that
it's pretty much just built in I'm not
even sure you can turn it off at this
point but yes absolutely everyone should
be using it most of the services that
you deploy to kubernetes aren't going to
need kubernetes permissions themselves
so you know my my web application
probably doesn't need kubernetes
permissions to talk to other stuff in
the cluster and so the service account
that that particular pod runs as should
have no permissions in the cluster and
then when we talk about users accessing
kubernetes and AD administrators
accessing kubernetes using those rback
roles very heavily is is definitely
recommended by kubernetes permissions do
you mean the service having a permission
to talk to some part of the kubernetes
control plane through a kubernetes API
correct yeah so some things need that
right we talked about controllers like
external DNS and CT manager they need to
be able to ask the kubernetes API about
what ingresses exist and what
annotations do they they have whereas
you know your web application shouldn't
need those permissions to talk to the
kubernetes API so looking at other
aspects of security there are a number
of things that have the word policy in
the kubernetes world we have a network
Nam space policies node policies
certainly role-based Access Control
could be considered policies although it
doesn't contain the word and then
there's another add-on called kerno
which is called a policy manager are
these to some extent completely
independent and we need all of them or
are they different solutions to the same
problem where you pick what's
appropriate in your situation how do you
navigate through this policy space
that's a great question we've kind of
done ourselves a disservice with the
policy word and overloading it in a few
places so the few things that you listed
I think cover very different areas and I
I'll kind of separate them out Network
policy is its own specific thing because
that is a kubernetes built-in API object
and that specifically dictates what
traffic can come in or out think of it
as a traditional firewall rule right for
your name space and so any pod in that
Nam space can't talk in or out based on
that Network policy and that's enforced
by the container networking interface
that we talked about earlier and so it's
it's a fairly lowlevel piece of policy
right we're talking about like at the IP
address level whatever my layers are a
little off in my head it was that layer
four so that's Network policy and that's
kind of its own category of things when
you start talking about caverno and
actually I'll shamelessly plug one of
our open source projects Polaris we're
talking about policy around what you can
and cannot do within the kubernetes API
it's sort of a a Twist on arbac right
arback says what you can do says that
you know this entity is allowed to
perform these verb on these nouns in the
cluster right and it can do those
different things whereas policy is more
saying you can't do these things and so
typically I think of it as like a lot of
times it looks like Json schema where
you have a specific set of things that
are allowed in this unstructured object
which is the Ku yaml or the structured
object sorry with loose definitions and
now we restrict that even further to say
you can't do this so that's a very
abstract way of talking about it I think
an easy way to talk about it is like by
default crimin lets you deploy resources
or pods that don't have a resource
request that just just just like put me
wherever I'll figure out how much
resources I need later well you can say
with policy that's not allowed to happen
in this cluster the criet API may allow
it but now my policy is further
restricting what it can can do in
kubernetes give an example of you said
one is you can't deploy a pod with
without a resource request give an
example of another policy that you could
Implement with kyero or Polaris of
something you can't do so by default
anytime you deploy a container into
kubernetes it runs as the root user so
and that's part of the security context
specification of a pod and that's
something you may not want to do so we
can restrict that with policy as well
and then there's privilege escalation
that's built in as well so like the
ability to pseudo and then different
capabilities that the container might
have have at the colonel level so like
capsis admin or things like that so you
can restrict all of those Sandy in the
time we have left we've covered a lot of
aspects decisions that you need to make
along the way to get your cluster up and
running are there any major areas that
need to be taken into account that we
haven't covered that's a good question I
think we covered a lot of the really
foundational stuff which is good I think
one area that we didn't talk about much
is how to deploy into kubernetes you
know you have your your Helm charts or
your customize like how you manage the
actual yaml that you deploy with and
then how that actually gets deployed
into the cluster is another thing to be
to be thinking about as part of your
kubernetes strategy what are some of the
major options in that area so Helm's a
very popular way to package up your yaml
it's a templating language essentially
that lets you you template out yaml and
then it has its own ability to deploy to
the cluster via Helm install and that
creates a release object and sort of the
life cycle that's one way that's popular
that we've done for a long time and then
the next kind of like big category of
things is the gitops tooling space where
we run sort of a Long Live process in
the cluster that watches a git
repository full of yaml or Helm charts
or however you want to package your yl
and then keeps the cluster up to date
with that repository so you don't
actually deploy you just make changes to
get I'll mention to listeners we have
episode 440 on getups and and 509 on
Helm charts Andy so to wrap up anything
you'd like to tell us about Fairwinds oh
so many good things to talk about with
Fairwinds but Fairwinds has been running
clusters for I mean I've been here for
five and a half years they were running
kubernetes two years before that so
since pretty much the very beginning of
kubernetes so our services arm can help
you run your clusters and help your team
you know bolster its kubernetes
knowledge or just run all of your
infrastructure for you if that's
something you want but then we talked
about our open source Polaris we have
other open source a lot of Open Source
Polaris Goldilocks Pluto arback manager
Nova and Gemini and yeah I think that's
most of them and all of these tools are
just ways to help you run kubernetes
better more reliably more securely and
then if you're interested in in running
our open source at scale along with
other open source including caverno and
then doing cost management we have a SAS
product that you can go check out we
have a free trial of it up to two
clusters so give that a shot at inside
sites. far.com would you like to point
listeners toward your presence on the
internet anywhere I'm not super present
on the internet I'm very active in the
cncf so various areas of the cncf slack
and the kubernetes slack and then
LinkedIn I am sudman JR sudman Jr just
about everywhere you can you can think
to find me so Andy sudman thank you very
much for speaking to software
engineering radio thank you for having
me it was a great time this says Ben
Robert blumen for software engineering
radio and thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by i e software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at
e-r. to provide feedback you can comment
on each episode on the website or reach
us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or
through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
c-ret the this and all other episodes of
SC radio is licensed under creative
comments license
2.5 thanks for